# Francesco Rota

▼ Zürcherstrasse 116, Birmensdorf, 8903, Schweiz +41765199312

rotafran@outlook.com

m www.linkedin.com/in/francescorota93/

## **ABOUT ME**

I am a Data Scientist with international academic experience in the natural sciences (BSc, MSc and PhD). I specialised in ecology, botany, GIS and data science. During my PhD I focused on machine learning applied to species distribution models. During my last postdoc I had the opportunity to work with spatial modelling and machine learning. I bring strong analytical thinking, attention to detail, and a passion for environmental data. I have extensive experience in data validation, spatial modeling, machine learning, and the use of HPC environments. My work involves developing reproducible pipelines, quality-checking large geospatial datasets, and writing clear technical reports and scientific papers. I like dealing with complex issues on a daily basis always with a high degree of personal commitment, responsibility, accuracy, and team spirit.

### SKILLS

- · Programming: R, Python, bash, SQL, LaTeX, C
- Technical Skills: data analyses, statistical modeling, predictive analytics, big data processing, machine learning, GIS, scientific writing
- · Tools: VS Code, RStudio, Linux, HPC, Slurm, Docker, Singularity, GoogleEarthEngine, QGIS, ArcGIS Pro, GitHub, Overleaf, Shiny, Office Suite
- Soft Skills: problem-solving, critical thinking, science communication, project management, knowledge sharing, teamwork, teaching

#### LANGUAGES

· Italiano native

- · English C1
- · German B1
- Spanish C1
- · French B1

## Professional Certificates

2024

Computer Science for Artificial Intelligence

ONLINE HARVARDX-EDX · Harvard University 9



2022

**Professional Habilitation** 

Albo degli Agrotecnici e degli AGROTECNICI LAUREATI · Ministero della Giustizia, Roma 💡



#### **PUBLICATIONS**

Google Scholar: https://scholar.google.com/citations? user=qOLAfo8AAAAJhl=deoi=ao

### EXPERIENCE

2022-2024

#### **Post-Doc Researcher**

GIS & DATA SCIENCE · Swiss Federal Institute for Forest Snow and Landscape Research WSL, Birmensdorf 9

Forest Resources and Management, Forest Biodiversity, Machine Learning, SDM, Digital Soil Maps, High Performance Computing

2021 **Visiting Researcher** 

Botany · Universität Innsbruck ♥ Genomics Lab, Bioinformatics, Population genomics, RADseq, Genetic Diversity, HPC



2018-2022

#### **Researcher & Teaching Assistant**

EcoLogy · Free University of Bozen-Bolzano ♥ Machine Learning, Data Science, Climate Change, Rare Alpine Endemic Plants, Species Distribution Models, Maps, Phylogeography; Teaching Assistant in Botany



2017

#### **Erasmus+ Trainee**

Ecological Monitoring · Universidad de La Laguna, Tenerife 9

Island Ecology, Ecological Restoration, Biodiversity Conservation, Data Science



#### EDUCATION

2018-2022

Mountain Environment & Agriculture · Free University of Bozen-Bolzano ♥

Major in Ecology, Environment and Protection of Mountain Areas



2015-2017

#### MSc

NATURAL SCIENCES · Università di Bologna ? Biometry and Statistics, Environmental Economy and Impact, Laboratory of Digital Mapping and GIS, Physiology of Plants, Speleology, Systematic Botany Laboratory, Vegetation Ecology



#### 2014 Erasmus+ fellowship

BIOLOGICAL AND ENVIRONMENTAL SCIENCES . Universidad de Salamanca 🕈



2012-2015

NATURAL SCIENCES · Università di Milano 9 Physical Geography and Cartography, Biology, Mathematics, Physics, Chemistry, Genetics, Physiology, Zoology, Botany, Ecology and Ethology, Conservation Biology, Geology, Oceanography, Renewable Energies



2012

#### **High School Diploma**

LICEO SCIENTIFICO WITH SPECIALIZATION IN PHYSICS · Istituto Andrea Fantoni, Clusone, Bergamo, Italy 9